<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Huon d'Auvergne, Kupferstichkabinett 78 D 8 (olim Hamilton 337)
                    Annotations</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <name xml:id="SPM">Stephen Patrick McCormick</name>
                    <resp>Annotations</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Washington and Lee University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Lexington, Virginia</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc xml:lang="en">
                    <!-- xml:id ??? See Cummings 52 -->
                    <!-- add encodingDesc -->
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>Germany</country>
                        <settlement>Berlin</settlement>
                        <repository>Kupferstichkabinett</repository>
                        <idno>78 D 8</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <divGen type="toc"/>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <note xml:id="b12" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: <hi rend="italic">une</hi>,(final -e is expunctuated)</note>
                <note xml:id="b55" type="codic" resp="#LZM"><hi rend = "italic">queus</hi> MS: <hi rend = "italic">quilens</hi> with a dot under each letter, "il" <ex rend="italic">i</ex>."</note>
                <note xml:id="b136" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> All text that is written above the line in the original is enclosed in parentheses in this transcription. </note>
                <note xml:id="b200" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> This line is problematic for sense; the Turin version is also unclear. </note>
                <note xml:id="b245" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: <hi rend="italic">revser</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="b343" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: <hi rend="italic">nolōs</hi> This is an interesting slip: <hi rend="italic">non</hi> added to a form of <hi rend="italic">voloir</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="b415" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> <hi rend="italic">ia belist</hi>. This is a hapax. Elsewhere in the text, we find <hi rend="italic">l'abelist</hi>, e.g., 4169, 6321, etc.</note>
                <note xml:id="b508" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> There is a "+" in the right margin in light brown ink, perhas inserted by a nineteenth-century reader.</note>
                <note xml:id="b542" type="ling" resp="#LZM"> Cf. <hi rend="italic">Entrée d'Espagne, gaumenter</hi> (TL <hi rend="italic">gaimenter</hi>)</note>
                <note xml:id="b674" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> The MS is difficult to read: 'r'of <hi rend="italic">complira</hi> is unclear.</note>
                <note xml:id="b751" type="codic" resp="#LZM">p<hi rend="italic">re</hi>gant: the "g" has an unusual form; it looks more like a "y"</note>
                <note xml:id="b790" type="interp" resp="#LZM">MS: <hi rend="italic">empial</hi>. Cf. vv. 47, 73, 373, etc., where we see <hi rend="italic">emp[er]ial</hi>. However, see <hi rend="italic">empir</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">Prise de Pampelune</hi> (v. 4970) and the many other variants. As one of the most frequent words in epic vocabulary, it is greatly varied in rhyme. Furthermore, in Italian, "empio" means "irreligioso, sacrilego, profanatore" and "spietato, crudele" (Zingarelli) so while there is the hint of emperor, there is also the sense of merciless, sacrilegious ruler.</note>
                <note xml:id="b818" type="ling" resp="#LZM"> MS:<hi rend="italic">abosdivoir</hi>. Cf. <hi rend="italic">Entrée d'Espagne bosdeor</hi>; <hi rend="italic">Guerra d'Attila bosder, bosdeor, bosdera, bosdie</hi>, etc.</note>
                <note xml:id="b888" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS:<hi rend="italic">confortas ɾoe</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="b923" type="ling" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">Tutore</hi>: cf. www.treccani.it/enciclopedia/tuttora_(Enciclopedia-Dantesca)/. Typical of Old Italian, found in Dante, the <hi rend="italic">Fiore</hi>, etc. Consulted Nov. 26, 2016.</note>
                <note xml:id="b948" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: <hi rend="italic">monreç</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="b960" type="ling" resp="#LZM">Note the Italianate construction of definite article + possessive.</note>
                <note xml:id="b977" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="italic">hair</hi>: this could be haïr, anger, but we are interpreting it as "air" to go with the Turin reading and also the sense here: out the window and into the air, the sky.</note>
                <note xml:id="b1149" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> <hi rend="italic">la</hi> is almost unreadable in the manuscript. It is unclear whether this was intentional or not on the part of the scribe or was done later; it seems to be something painted over those letters, but similar to a spot on the left side of the page of a chocolate or cafeaulait color.</note>
                <note xml:id="b1152" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Catchword at the bottom of the page, almost entirely washed out:<hi rend="italic">si</hi> </note>
                <note xml:id="b1159" type="ling" resp="#LZM">There are three other forms (<hi rend="italic">aflicions</hi> twice, <hi rend="italic">aflicion</hi> once), all in rhyme position. Therefore I here presume <hi rend="italic">aflicion</hi> as the base form, here elided with the preposition <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="b1250" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> Between lines 1249 and 1250 in column 9va, running into the right margin is a line with an "x"; also at the bottom of column 9va, there is a line with a corresponding "x" in the left margin. Since the column is one line too long in comparison to the other, and normally the columns are equal, this final line (1264) is clearly to be moved to the position between 1249 and 1250.</note>
                <note xml:id="b1361" type="interp" resp="#JCV"><hi rend="italic">Sir</hi> désigne la ville de Tyr, puisque les tissus d'Orient étaient réputés et [...] l'on indique volentiers une ville d'Orient comme lieu d'où provient un tissu précieux. ("Sir" refers to the city Tyre, since oriental fabrics were famous and a famous city of the East is frequently used as a source for a valuable fabric (trans. LZM)).</note>
                <note xml:id="b1399" type ="interp" resp="#LZM"> MS:<hi rend="italic">ma[n]dana</hi>, however it seems most likely to be an error for "via[n]da na"; cf. line 6181 <hi rend="italic">viande n'a</hi>.
                <note xml:id="b1643" type ="interp" resp="#LZM"> The rhyme here is normally a diphthongue but the simple past of <hi rend="italic">oïr</hi> is bisyllabic, so the editor must choose between the rhyme spellings or the usual representation of the simple past of this verb. See also 8160, 11274.</hi>.
                <note xml:id="b1749" type ="codic" resp="#LZM"> The MS is damaged at this point and extremely difficult to read. T: morty zasere al sabione [dead men lying on the sand]. If the reading here were similar, it might be <hi rend="italic">hon veit sor ce gravois</hi>; but the two are not always parallel. <hi rend="italic">Gravoy</hi> appears appears five times, <hi rend="italic">gravois</hi> once, in this text, meaning "sand" or "gravel" in some way (path, etc.) in this MS.</hi>.

                <note xml:id="b9915" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> The illumination at the bottom of this page is of a city with five towers visible, a figure in red (with head covering) at the top of the first gate on the left, nearest the three visitors who are at the far left. The gate figure holds a book with black dots to represent writing on it. Note that the tower is square, suggesting that "reont" refers to something else. <hi rend="ital">Charere</hi> (line 9915) means both "chair" (<hi rend="ital">cattedra</hi> in MSI) and "highway" in this text, as confirmed by other Franco-Italian texts. In fact, the gateway is rounded and the human figure is at the highest point. Since this is a scholar with a book, it makes the most sense for him to be in a chair or seat.  The portion remaining in the Turin MS (folio 146R) shows a loggia with rounded openings to the left of the illumination, with the three travellers outside to the left. One figure inside (with a fancy headdress) is on a chair with a baldacchino in a polygonal shape (not quite a circle, but circular) above. Since the walls in the Berlin MS illumination reach outside the frame, there is nothing above the figure who is on top of the gate there. It is unclear therefore whether the Turin version is a variation of meaning, but in any case, it is one possible explanation
                of <hi rend="ital">reont</hi>.</note>
                <note xml:id="b9935" type="refer" resp="#LZM"> There are several historical figures by the name Nicomachus to whom this may refer. Aristotle's father and son were both so named; the <title rend="ital">Nichomachean Ethics</title>, a compendium of Aristotle's notes (or Aristotle's notes plus Nichomachus's comments on them)  may have been dedicated to the son. Nicomachus of Gerasa, who lived in the first century AD, was a mathematician about whom little is known. His work on the magical properties of numbers and a manual on harmonics, an early discussion of musical theory and pitch. Various other works of his were lost. Since there are references to necromacy in this section, the second identity seems more likely.(Thanks to AEB for assistance in identifying the name.)</note>
                <note xml:id="b9947" type="interp" resp="LZM">T: Un nome scrisse sopra la porta de sussa.</note>
                <note xml:id="b9950" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Farabus: al-Farabi, a great Arabic philosopher, known as Alpharabius in the West, viewed as the "second master" after Aristotle. He lived in the 9th-10th centuries and was known for scientific (which include mathematical and musical works) and philosophical writings (again, thanks to AEB for identifying the figure). </note>
                <note xml:id="b9951" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> See translation for a delineation of speakers in this exchange."</note>
                <note xml:id="b9972" type="codic" resp="#LZM">-t of ce<hi rend="italic">r</hi>t very smeared and difficult to distinguish exc. in ms. itself.</note>
                <note xml:id="b9982" type="interp" resp="#LZM">MS: da sa: Turin, pasate; perhaps from "danser" or "dechacier"; it indicates movement forward; cf. Dante, Inf. 3.51: "ma guarda e passa"</note>
                <note xml:id="b9989" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> <hi rend="ital">-ent</hi> of ending, -o changed to e. </note>
                <note xml:id="b10004" type="codic" resp="#LZM">The line is complete, but something is clearly missing for the sense here; cf. T: <hi rend="italic">Dize lo [con]te a Eneas, chy lo mena</hi> [The count asks Aeneas, who leads him]. Br similarly reads Dist li quens Ugues ad Eneas qi lo maine  (v. 1117).</note>
                  <!--this line needs a second type, interp-->
                <note xml:id="b10029" type="codic" resp="#LZM">'e' above the line with caret below.</note>
                <note xml:id="b10037" type="interp" resp="#LZM">This could be either "fit il" or "fit, 'il n'est'" without a difference in meaning.</note>
                <note xml:id="b10051" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> 'pure' below the line into the edge of the page.</note>
                <note xml:id="b10053" type="codic" resp="#LZM">(e) is in the binding. MS 'oscüe'</note>
                <note xml:id="b10062" type="codic" resp="#LZM">sc[r](i)pture: i above the line as abbreviation.</note>
                <note xml:id="b10071" type="interp" resp="#LZM">In this manuscript there are two forms: <ex rend="italic">par poy</ex> (2 appearances) and <ex rend="italic">por poy</ex> (one appearance), but only <ex rend="italic">por</ex> appears with <ex rend="italic">val</ex> and its derivatives. Mixed lists are not unknown, so I have resolved thus here.</note>
                <note xml:id="b10075" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS: cu[m] The abbreviation mark here is in the form of a vertical  "z"; cf. Viellard, <ex rend="italic">Conseils</ex>, Vol. 1, p. 28, # 11.</note>
                <note xml:id="b10093" type="refer" resp="#LZM"> These are all Saracens from <ex rend="italic">Aspremont</ex>: Agolant is the ruler of the Saracens, father of Helmont, and killed by Girard's nephew Claire. Uliens is one of Agolant's judges, an important Saracen in the second half of the poem, killed by Richier, grandson of Duke Berengier.</note>
                <note xml:id="b10105" type="refer" resp="#LZM">This does not follow the French version of <ex rend="italic">Aspremont</ex>; Roland killed Eaumont (=Helmont=Almonte). There is nothing about Helmont sleeping. See laisses 286-7 in Suard's edition. The sleeping recalls the motif of Roland killing Ferragu in the <ex rend="italic">Entrée d'Espagne</ex>, where Ferragu took a nap using a rock as a pillow, and Roland was tempted to kill him with a stone  (vv. 3535-3555).</note>
                <note xml:id="b10108" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Stengel here proposes the emendation <ex rend="italic">(homes)</ex> after .jj. to follow the plot of <ex rend="italic">Aspremont</ex>, where Roland kills Eaumont on the second day of the battle. However, <jors> seems more appropriate for that reason. Cf. F. Suard, ed., <ex rend="italic">Aspremont: Chanson de geste du XIIe siècle</ex>, Champion 2008, vv. 3897-5545.</note>
                <note xml:id="b10142" type="codic" resp="#LZM">'canter' has a mark above the 'c', like an apostrophe- meaning unclear, but definitely ink and not a defect in the parchment. T: cercare</note>
                <note xml:id="b10148" type="refer" resp="#LZM">"Death by chessboard" is a chanson de geste motif: in the <ex rend="italic">Geste Francor</ex>, Ogier the Dane kills Charlot, Charlemagne's son, with a chessboard; in Renaut de Montauban, Bertholet has died thus also, and further incidents appear in the Batârd de Bouillon and in Parise la duchesse, but there is no known incident relating to Thibaut killing his brother-in-law Folco in the East. On chess in the Middle Ages and its uses, see Jenny Adams, <ex rend="italic">Power Play: The Literature and Politics of Chess in the Late Middle Ages</ex>, U of Penn P, 2006; Nicholas Perkins, ed., <ex rend="italic">Medieval Romance and Medieval Culture</ex>, D. S. Brewer, 2015. An Italian novella, in fact, insists on Thibaut's family relationship to Guillaume through Folco (married to Anfelise, Thibaut's stepsister, niece of Desramé), <ex rend="italic">I Conti di antichi cavalieri</ex>, ed. Alberto del Monte Cisalpino-Goliardica, 1972, pp. 118-22.</note>
                <note xml:id="b10158" type="codic" resp="#LZM">The illumination at the bottom of this page, 70V, has three parts. Starting at the left, the three men travelling through Hell, Guillaume in front and frontal; Huon to his left and side view; and Aeneas barely visible behind Guillaume's right. In the middle is a lady, side view, in a fancy purple dress with gold decorations; and to the right is a crowned man on a white horse with his sword raised to strike. His trappings are all gold- spurs, saddle, bit. </note>
                <note xml:id="b10177" type="codic" resp="#LZM">MS este followed by expunctuated <ex rend="italic">-e</ex>: dots both below and above.</note>
                <note xml:id="b10182" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> <ex rend="italic">Guilla[u]me</ex>: there is an abbreviation apostrophe after the two <ex rend="italic">ll</ex>'s, so though the name is usually spelled <ex rend="italic">Guillame</ex> in the text we have added the <ex rend="italic">u</ex> here.</note>
                <note xml:id="b10188" type="refer" resp="#LZM"> Dante, <ex rend="italic">Inf</ex>.,3.103-105.</note>
                <note xml:id="b10196" type="codic" resp="#LZM">This is the first part of the illumination at the foot of 71R: three men are outside a city wall, within which (center) is a knight without a head covering, but a beard and long haïr, in flames. He wears armor covered by a yellow tunic decorated with black G's.</note>
                <note xml:id="b10203" type="codic" resp="#LZM">This is the second part of the illumination on 71R, to the right. Inside the city wall, devils are pushing that same figure (in yellow with black G's) into a cave opening (Hell, one presumes).</note>
                <note xml:id="b10206" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Girardo au Fraite [de Vienne] is a chanson de geste character, lord of Burgundy, Milon's brother, father of Rainier, grandfather of Oliver according to the <ex rend="italic">Geste Francor</ex>. He revolted against Charlemagne, refusing to aid him in Aspremont. René Louis, <ex rend="italic">De l'histoire à la légende</ex>, 3 vols, Imprimerie moderne, 1946-47, proposes various theories about the multiple Girards in chansons de geste. </note>
                <note xml:id="b10225" type="codic" resp="#LZM">After 'laig', letter scratched out; again looks like white-out over the spot.</note>
                <note xml:id="b10243" type="refer" resp="#LZM">There are no other forms of this as noun or as adjective. However, the suffix <ex rend="italic">-borg</ex> does appear, where <ex rend="italic">-urg</ex> does not. "The Burgundian" is Girard, lord of Vienne, known not only for his pride but his fierce fighting against the Saracens.</note>
                <note xml:id="b10246" type="codic" resp="#LZM">'non vaut si' is written over a scratch-out.</note>
                <note xml:id="b10247" type="codic" resp="#LZM">The "bone" is very hard to read because of a black smear at the top of the folio that almost completely covers it.</note>
                <note xml:id="b10305" type="codic" resp="#LZM">Po[st]és: cf forms of "e[st]." T: per fare a luy dalmazo, si aveseno posanza, v. 9959.</note>
                <note xml:id="b10321" type="refer" resp="#LZM">Again, cf. Dante and Virgil- Filippo Argenti? </note>
                <note xml:id="b10329" type="interp" resp="#LZM">Tisiaus: Tisias is reported to have been the first theoretician of rhetoric in ancient Greece. It is taken that he was the student of one Corax, who has left no written work. Tradition has it that, after the fall of the monarchy in Sicily in the 5th c. BCE, the rise of democracy occasioned a need for persuasive speech (command no longer being accepted). One successful Sicilian practitioner was Gorgias who went to Athens in 427 BCE, where he became a major figure among the Sophists. In the <title rend="italic">Gorgias</title>, Plato accused rhetoricians of favoring opinion over truth, success in the moment over enduring verities. (See also <title rend="italic">Phaedrus</title> 267a-b.) Thus, in the history of rhetoric, Tisias would stand in the same relationship to rhetoric as the Sophists to sophistry. Support for this view comes in the theory that Corax was not a separate person, but that the word, which means "crow" is actually a derogatory nickname for Tisias himself. Rhetoric received a higher standing with Aristotle, fascinated with how things break down into their component parts, who wrote
                his <title rend="italic">Rhetoric</title> as an analytical guide to, and practical manual for, the art—but he distinguished it from logic (dialectic).  In the later Middle Ages, therefore, Tisias may be taken as a mythical founder, an archetype for all who
                indulge in untruth for  emotional effect. Whatever his reputation in antiquity, in this passage, Berlin, lines 10324-10351, Tisias seems to represent all seven liberal arts (10328). The reference to his singing includes another of the seven: grammar, logic, rhetoric, arithmetic, geometry, astronomy, and music. Wilfred Major, Epicharmus, Tisias, and the Early History of Rhetoric, <title rend="italic">Harvard Studies in Classical Philology</title> 107 (2013), 55-72; A. G. Hinks, "Tisias and Corax and the Invention of Rhetoric," <title rend="italic">The Classical Quarterly</title> 34,1/2 (Jan.-Apr., 1940), 61-69. (Alan E. Bernstein).</note>
                <note xml:id="b10335" type="interp" resp="#LZM"> This scene may refer to the beginning of the mass; at that era, the "introit involves the singing of a Psalm, which by this period would have been sung alternatingly by two choir bodies," and that might account for the "a bis" idea. Alternatively, it may be like improvisory practice where "one singer or group of singers would sing the original chant tune, and the other voices might improvise or sing composed counterpoint above it" and "vocal polyphony was used during mass, often with a low line carrying the chant tune, and upper voices providing countermelodies, improvised or otherwise." Where and when it was done and if the celebrant was involved would be difficult to verify since the specific origin of this story is not known. We thank Remi Chiu, Assoc. Prof. of Fine Arts (Music) at LUM for his collaboration.</note>
                <note xml:id="b10337" type="codic" resp="#LZM">There appears to have been a <hi rend="italic">saut de même au même</in> in an original text here, since both B and T repeat the same verb in two lines in a row. The second would be more likely "dit"/"dist" or "fait."</note>
                <note xml:id="b10345" type="ling" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="ital">Scure</hi> appears twice in the text; obscure or oscure in various forms, seven times. There are no forms with an <hi rend="italic">a-</hi> prefix.</note>
                <note xml:id="10363" type="interp" resp="#LZM"><hi rend="ital">ras</hi>: Turin has "rasy", shorn, but in OF "ras" can also mean "guilty." That however would not be immediately visible to the bystander.</note>
                <note xml:id="10374" type="interp" resp="#LZM">The construction of this line is somewhat unclear: <hi rend="ital">croie</ex> is clear in the MS; in T the line is also problematic. Cf. line 420, <hi rend="ital">cro ge</ex>.</note>

                <note xml:id="b15000" type="codic" resp="#LZM"> Template note </note>
                </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
